Hey בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is לה, lamed hey,
we're דף ה, daf hey,
and we're going to pick up at the bottom of לד עמוד
ב. lamed daled amud beis. Now I wanted to just review what
we said yesterday because I also realized that I made a slight
mistake, and actually today is the whole remainder of the דף daf
today for those that enjoy the whole כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat
u'klal thing, that's what the whole דף daf is devoted to today,
is those hermeneutic rules, so get ready for a lot of fun.
Okay, so here is the point here, which is that it
maybe would be worth it to quickly read it in the
גמרא, Gemara, but let me just say the rule and then say
what I misstated yesterday. The basic rules are the following in terms
of כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, which is
the following and we'll do כלל ופרט klal u'prat and then ריבוי
ומיעוט. ribuy u'miut. Here's the rules: if you're of the כלל ופרט
klal u'prat category approach, which is the רבי ישמעאל Rebbi Yishmael approach,
so when you have a כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, what you are
left with is the פרט. prat. They understand תוספות Tosafot raises the
question why do you have to write the כלל, klal, but forget
that, we won't worry about that. The bottom line is that in
the end of the day, it ends with the final statement, the
final statement is the second statement is the final one.
פרט וכלל, prat u'klal, you basically, and the פרט, prat, כלל klal
is most of the פרט. prat. So basically those cases you're just
left with the second. You have כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u'klal
basically and then you have anything like the פרט. prat. Okay, what
our גמרא Gemara also introduced based on the fact of מיין ושכר
יזיר miyayin v'shechar yazir which is a פרט, prat, only יין ושכר,
yayin v'shechar, חומץ יין וחומץ chometz yayin v'chometz whatever, מכל אשר יעשה
mikol asher ye'atzeh is a כלל, klal, מחרצנים ועד זג לא יאכל
mchartanim v'ad zag lo yochel is a פרט,
prat, is that it's pretty much
the same at the end of today's דף daf we will see
that it's slightly different, but it's pretty much the same as a
פרט וכלל ופרט, prat u'klal u'prat, also gets you into like the
פרט, prat, because if you think about it, if you just had
a כלל ופרט klal u'prat here, if you had ended here, you
would have said just the פרט. prat. Comes the כלל klal and
that broadens it, anything like the פרט. prat. Okay, if you had
a פרט וכלל prat u'klal here, you would have said
everything, פרט וכלל prat u'klal is everything. Comes the פרט prat and
it pulls it in a little bit. So either way here you
get anything like the פרט. prat.
Okay, 100%, it's like there's really two categories what you're saying.
Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to talk about a slight difference.
Okay, so that's what we did yesterday and we said that מיין
ושכר יזיר, miyayin v'shechar yazir, מכל אשר mikol asher is a פרט,
prat, מכל אשר יעשה mikol asher ye'atzeh is a כלל, klal, מחרצנים
mchartanim is a פרט, prat, so פרט וכלל ופרט prat u'klal u'prat
is also like the פרט prat and anything that's פרי ופסולת פרי.
pri v'psolet pri. So פרי pri is it doesn't have to be
a גמר פרי, gmar pri, it could be actually something
unripe, okay, that's like which is ענבים לחים ויבשים anavim lachim v'yeveshim
is a פרי, pri, but anything even unripe and a פסולת פרי
psolet pri like חומץ chometz is a type of a spoiled wine,
so some type of a spoiled grape. Okay, so that's what we
learned out, we learned פרי, pri, even unripe, and we learned from
the fact ענבים anavim is פרי, pri, anything like that is even
unripe grapes, and חומץ chometz is a פסולת, psolet, so anything like
that even spoiled grapes. That's what we did yesterday. Now, so that's
number one. Now, if you however hold of מיעוט וריבוי, miut v'ribuy,
if that's your approach and here's where I slightly misstated it yesterday.
If you hold of מיעוט וריבוי, miut v'ribuy, let's first look at
this, if you have a,
let's start with
this, ריבוי ומיעוט, ribuy u'miut, so because basically this one seems to
be somewhat more logical, this one says like obviously you're not going
to, it's all going to get conflated into the second terms and
why did you need the first term, right? So if you have
a broad and a narrow, that's already going to lead you towards
a type of an abstraction and to say anything like the narrow
because why did you start with a broad term if you only
meant that? So this is already going to jump you into like
this second category, it's going to be anything like the מיעוט. miut.
מיעוט miut here's the same as the פרט. prat. Okay, that's already
going to abstract you. Okay, that's fine. The question, the things that
I misstated yesterday was that if you have מיעוט וריבוי, miut v'ribuy,
there because you end with a broader term,
what that gets you, the very fact that here you end with
a broad, you start narrow but you end broad, the fact that
you end broad, remember according to this approach it would have been
everything, because you ended broad. This says everything with a little bit
of a pullback. So this category does not have a parallel here,
which is
everything except what's most unlike, most dissimilar, dissimilar, okay. So according to,
so that's what you have with, that's what you have. Now, if
you notice according to this then... what you're going to get when
you have, okay, so those are the basic two ideas. The idea
of having a triple is not even so necessary because you sort
of already get the broadenings of basic broadening and extreme broadening already
with a double. You see that? Like ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u-miut you
already get one abstraction. It starts broad, it pulls it back, so
you get anything like the מיעוט. miut. מיעוט וריבוי miut u-ribui it
starts ends wide, so you only exclude things that are not dissimilar.
So the idea of a triple is not even so obvious what
function that would serve. Okay, so we're going to discuss that later
in today's דף. daf. But the point here is basically the מיעוט
וריבוי miut ve-ribui principle basically gets used, basic abstractions at the double
level. And if there's any function of a triple for that, for
that is unclear. Alright, so that's why if you'll notice, and this
is what caused me to pause yesterday, when it dealt with the
מיעוט וריבוי, miut ve-ribui, it only, it did not mention three terms,
it only mentioned two. So let's quickly, hold on, I want to
just quickly re-read that and we'll, so we'll pick up in the
middle of ל"ד עמוד ב' Lamed-Dalet Amud-Bet and then I'll take questions.
But let's just, now that we have that clear, let's just read
this in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
So we're going to go quickly, but I think it's worth it
to quickly re-read from, it's actually the middle of ל"ד עמוד ב',
Lamed-Dalet Amud-Bet, במאי קמיפלגי. be-mai kamiflagi. It's about ten lines down after
the גמרא Gemara begins, after the ג"מ gimmel mem the big ג"מ
גמרא gimmel mem Gemara begins. במאי קמיפלגי, be-mai kamiflagi, beginning of the
line. רבי אליעזר דריש ריבויי ומיעוטי. Rabbi Eliezer darish ribui u-miutei. Now
remember, Rabbi Eliezer is the one that says basically you could be
חייב chayav for anything except the wood itself. רבנן דרשי כלל ופרט.
Rabbanan darshi klal u-prat. רבי אליעזר דריש ריבויי ומיעוטי. Rabbi Eliezer darish
ribui u-miutei. מיין ושכר יזיר miyayin ve-shechar yazir מיעט. mi'et.
That's a limiting term. מכל אשר יעשה מגפן היין mikol asher ye'aseh
mi-gefen hayayin ריבה. riba. Okay, so that's A, right, מיין ושכר miyayin
ve-shechar and מכל אשר יעשה. mikol asher ye'aseh.
He doesn't care about the last term, he only cares about these
two terms. So that's a מיעוט וריבוי, miut ve-ribui, okay, ריבוי. ribui.
It ends with, so you're already basically everything except what is most
dissimilar. Okay, everybody with me? מיעוט וריבוי miut u-ribui it ends with
the broadening term. It's, you're not everything, that would be if your
כלל ופרט וכלל klal u-prat u-klal would be everything, but you're everything
except that which is most dissimilar. מאי ריבה? ריבה כל מילי. mai
riba? riba kol milei. So that basically the ריבוי ribui at the
end includes everything. מאי מיעט? מיעט שבישתא. mai mi'et? mi'et shevishta. It
excludes that which is most dissimilar, it excludes wood. So he only
focuses on the first two terms, ריבה ומיעט, riba ve-mi'et, מיעט וריבה.
mi'et ve-riba. He ends with a ריבה, riba, ריבוי. ribui. So therefore
he is, includes everything except that which is most dissimilar. Grape leaves
would be included. So that's Rabbi Eliezer's position, that grape leaves are
included. Okay, so that's Rabbi Eliezer. He ignores the third term, מחרצנים
ועד זג. mechartsannim ve-ad zag. רבנן Rabbanan and the Rabbis, דרשי כלל
ופרט. darshi klal u-prat. מיין ושכר miyayin ve-shechar פרט. prat. יזיר yazir
פרט. prat. Okay, that's the narrow. מכל אשר יעשה מגפן היין mikol
asher ye'aseh mi-gefen hayayin כלל. klal. מחרצנים ועד זג mechartsannim ve-ad zag
חזר ופרט. chazar ve-prat. So they focus on the third term. They
get a פרט כלל ופרט. prat klal u-prat. פרט כלל ופרט, אי
אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. prat klal u-prat, i attah dan ela
ke-ein haprat. מה הפרט מפורש פרי ופסולת פרי. ma haprat meforash pri
u-psolet pri. So פרי pri meaning just like the grape is a
פרי, pri, anything that's a פרי pri even if it's not ripened,
even unripened. ופסולת פרי u-psolet pri the same way חומץ chometz is
some type of a spoiled wine, wine or spoiled wine. Right,
so therefore anything that's even a spoiled grape. So that's how we're
broadening it.
אף כל פרי ופסולת פרי. af kol pri u-psolet pri. אי מה
הפרט מפורש פרי גמור אף כל פרי גמור. iy ma haprat meforash
pri gamur af kol pri gamur. One minute, maybe we should demand
a fully ripened fruit. No, אמרת אם כן מה הניח לך כתוב
במשמעות שלא אמרו. amarta im ken ma hiniach lecha katuv b'mashmaut shelo
amaro. So if that's what it means, like a fully good and
ripened fruit, then there's nothing that we're broadening, there's nothing we're including
based on this דרשה. drasha. ענבים לחים ויבשים הא כתיבי. anavim lachim
ve-yeveshim ha-ketivei. ייין וחומץ הא כתיבי. yayin ve-chometz ha-ketivei. So it can't
be that it's you need all you know it's fully ripened and
fully good, that's already in the פסוקים. psukim. הא לא לך ללכת
לדון כלל שאחרונו כלשון ראשונו. ha lo lach lalech ladun klal she-acharonu
ke-lashon rishono. So it's coming to teach you that it's anything even
somewhat like that, you know, it's abstract, is similar to that, which
means even unripened and even somewhat spoiled. Okay, that's if you do
פרט וכלל ופרט, prat u-klal u-prat, but you're not going to include
the leaves. Okay, because it still has to be fundamentally like the
פרט. prat. Okay, so. הא שסופנו לרבות כל דבר מה תלמוד לומר
מחרצנים ועד זג. ha she-sofenu lerabbot kol davar ma talmud lomar mechartsannim
ve-ad zag.
So why did it need the מחרצנים ועד זג, mechartsannim ve-ad zag,
which is now pretty obvious why it needed it, because you needed
it to create the פרט כלל ופרט prat klal u-prat structure. Which
is what it's going to tell you. לומר לך כל מקום שאתה
מוצא פרט וכלל. lomar lecha kol mako she-atta motzei prat u-klal. If
you had just had the פרט וכלל, prat u-klal, אי אתה רשאי
למשכנו לדון כעין הפרט. i attah rashai la-asholo ladun ke-ein haprat. You
would not have limited it to the פרט prat if you had
just ended with the פרט וכלל. prat u-klal. You would have said
everything. אלא נטה כלל מוסיף על הפרט. ela natta klal mosif al
haprat. It would, כלל klal would have included everything if you just
had a פרט וכלל. prat u-klal. עד שיפרוט לך הכתוב כדרך שפרט
לך בנזיר ad sheyifrot lecha hakatuv k'derech she-parat lecha binazir until you
needed the final פרט prat which is going to pull you back
like we have here. So פרט וכלל ופרט prat u-klal u-prat told
you don't say everything, say similar to the פרט, prat, פרי ופסולת
פרי. pri u-psolet pri. So again, for Rabbi Eliezer he just focuses
on these two, מיין ושכר מכל אשר יעשה. miyayin ve-shechar mikol asher
ye'aseh. It's a מיעט וריבוי. mi'et ve-ribui. Because it's a מיעוט וריבוי
miut v'ribuy
because if it was כלל ופרט klal u'prat and he ended here
he would have said everything, but because it's a מיעוט וריבוי miut
v'ribuy it doesn't say everything. It ends with a broad statement, but
the first מיעוט miut pulls back a little and says except for
that which is most dissimilar. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer winds up
having, excluding just the wood itself, but leaves you're חייב chayav because
basically he ignores this final thing. He said it's a מיעוט וריבוי:
miut v'ribuy: anything except that which is most dissimilar. וחכמים V'Chachamim say
כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat v'klal, which, okay, which is same as
כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat v'klal, פרט כלל ופרט. prat klal u'prat.
So it's anything similar to the פרט. prat. So any type of
grape, yes, even unripe, even spoiled, but not the leaves. Okay, and
that's the basic difference: which דרשה drasha do you do? And relatedly
is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer ignores the third term. And we're going
to just get to, if you're from the מיעוט וריבוי miut v'ribuy
camp, what do you do when there are three terms? But he
basically ignores the three terms because you basically already have the two
types of abstraction occurring already with two terms. Alright, let's just read
one more line to finish up what we did yesterday and then
I'll take if there's any questions. אמר מר: Amar mar: מה פרט
מפורש פרי ופסולת פרי אף כל פרי ופסולת פרי. Ma prat meforash
pri u'psolet pri af kol pri u'psolet pri. פרי Pri is ענבי,
invei, grapes. פסולת פרי מאי היא? Psolet pri mai hi? חומץ. Chometz.
What would be some type of a spoiled thing that's in the
פסוק? pasuk? So that would be vinegar. אף כל פרי, Af kol
pri, so then we're coming to broaden, what's the broadening if you're
in the כלל פרט וכלל klal prat v'klal camp? So מאי היא?
mai hi? גוהרקא, Goharki, which is unripe grapes, or unripe in general.
אף כל פסולת פרי מאי היא? Af kol psolet pri mai hi?
What's the inclusion of things that are like, you know, spoiled? אמר
רב כהנא Amar Rav Kahana לאתויי ענבי דכרין l'atuyei invei dichrin or
some say דכדום dichdum or whatever, but basically it means some type
of a wormy or rotting grape. Okay, now we have one last
question: ועד זג. V'ad zag. Now, what do we
do with ועד זג? V'ad zag? Is that coming to tell you
something? What's like ועד? v'ad? Why didn't it say מחרצנים ועד זג
לא יאכל? mechartzanim v'zag lo yochel? So now it's like a slightly
different point, not a כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat v'klal point, but
what's like ועד זג v'ad zag coming to tell you? So ועד
זג, v'ad zag, אמר רבינא: Amar Ravina: לאתויי דביני ביני, l'atuyei de-beini
beinei, the stuff in between. Now what do you mean in between?
תוספות Tosafot has two interesting explanations. The simplest explanation is if חרצנים
chartzanim are the pits and זג zag is the skin, so from
חרצנים chartzanim to the זג, zag, you run into the whole flesh
in the middle. That's ביני ביני. beini beinei. But תוספות Tosafot says
who needs a פסוק pasuk for that? I mean, that's like the
grape itself. He says no, maybe you would have thought that if
somebody scraped out just the flesh and left behind the pits and
the skin, that would be like a type of לא דרך אכילה.
lo derech achila. You know, normal people don't eat grapes, I mean
unless you're doing it for your kids, then maybe you're peeling it
and maybe
you're removing. Normal people don't like do that. So who knows? Maybe
you were thought that if you had just eaten that, that would
have been some type of a שינוי shinuy or something like that
and you would have gotten off the hook. So that's one explanation
he says, which is truly the simple sense of ביני ביני, beini
beinei, although it's a weird הוה אמינא. hava amina. The other explanation
he means is like the tiny grapes that grow between the grapes
that are fully developed. And those grapes are like not exposed to
the sun and they're never going to ripen and he says that's
even a slightly different category than unripe, because unripe just hasn't had
time yet to ripen, but it will ripen. These grapes won't ripen
at all, so that's maybe what it's coming to include. So somehow
ועד זג, v'ad zag, I don't know, I don't know. That's why
the first reading is the easier one.
Anyway,
now we're going to unpack it, but there were some questions from
before. Yes.
So I have two questions. One is, is it possible, despite the
fact that the סוגיא sugya is attempting to compare these terminologies and
distinguish between them, is it possible that what we're looking at are
two different hermeneutic schools completely with two different sets of terminology?
Yeah, that's what we said the other day, which is that the
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael is כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, ריבוי ומיעוט ribuy
u'miut is רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
And it's exactly, it's basically the different use of terms just to
express, meaning the words are the same, they're broad terms or they're
narrow terms. The question is what are your hermeneutics? So whether you
use the terminology of כלל ופרט klal u'prat or מיעוט וריבוי miut
v'ribuy reflects which hermeneutic school you're coming from, which hermeneutic approach you're
coming from. Right.
And just a question on a word: when the גמרא Gemara asks
מאי מיעט מיעט
שבישתא? Mai miyatei miyatei shabishta? Do you read that word שבישתא shabishta
like a bird or שבשתא shabeshta like it was a mistake?
Neither. שבישתא shabishta is the Aramaic word for like a stick. רש"י
Rashi quotes a גמרא Gemara where it speaks about a certain אמורא
Amora that would dance before the כלה kalla with a שבישתא, shabishta,
with a wood from a tree or whatever. Yeah, so it's, the
שין shin is
part of the root. Yeah.
What's the underlying rationale, not רש"י, Rashi,
תוספות, Tosafot, excuse me, in
ignoring the third qualification?
Well, we're not ignoring it. We're going to do something with it.
We're going to discuss in a minute what we do with it.
Well, he hasn't dealt with it yet. We're not done. But he's
not using it in his מיעוט וריבוי miut v'ribuy דרשה. drasha. He's
going to get to what he does with that. That's what we're
about to turn to. Okay. Now the question would be, if you
didn't, he's going to have something to do with this term, but
if you didn't have something to do with the problem we have
here, what do we need that? Is it the כלל ופרט? klal
u-ferat? You have a פרט וכלל... perat u-klal... פרט כלל ופרט. perat
klal u-perat. The גמרא Gemara is going to deal with it.
No, the כלל
ופרט?
klal u-ferat?
You have a פרט כלל ופרט. perat klal u-perat.
The גמרא Gemara is
going to deal with it. All of your questions, trust me, that's
what today's דף daf is about. Every, I mean I'm not sure
all of them, but a lot of them are going to be
addressed in today's דף. daf. Let's take a look. אמר
מר. Amar mar. Okay, now.
So let's go back and look at what we discussed before. Okay.
אם פרט מפורש פרי גמור אף כל פרי גמור אמרת אם כן
מה הניח לך הכתוב במשמעו של מחרצנים ועד זג. Im perat meforash
peri gamur af kol peri gamur amarta im ken mah hiniach lecha
hakatuv bemashma’o shel mechartzanim ve-ad zag. In the end you tried to
say it had to be fully developed, then there would be nothing
that this abstraction would include that's not explicit in the פסוק. pasuk.
ענבים לחים ויבשים הכתיב יין וחומץ הכתיב. Anavim lachim viyveshim haktiv yayin
vechometz haktiv. הא אין לך לדון כלשון אחרון אלא כלשון ראשון. Ha
ein lecha ladun keleshon acharon ella keleshon rishon. Okay ומאחר, umai-achar, so
clearly we mean that we're abstracting it. ומאחר שסופנו לרבות כל דבר
מה תלמוד לומר מחרצנים ועד זג? Umai-achar shesofenu lerabbot kol davar mah
talmud lomar mechartzanim ve-ad zag? So then if we're going to include
everything, which is because we didn't include everything, you know we only
included similar, not everything. So the גמרא Gemara says so why did
we need the פרט? perat? ואומר לך כל מקום שאתה מוצא פרט
וכלל שהיה בסופו פרט אי אתה רשאי למושכו ולדונו כעין הפרט. Ve-omer
lecha kol makom she-attah motze perat u-klal she-hayah besofo perat i attah
rashai le-moshcho u-leduno ke-ein ha-perat.
You would not have come to a conclusion that you needed similar
to the פרט, perat, אלא נעשה כלל מוסיף על הפרט. ella na’aseh
klal mosif al ha-perat.
You would have said that the כלל klal would have been all-inclusive.
So you the reason you needed the final פרט perat was to
make it not all-inclusive, to say that it had to be somewhat
similar to the פרט. perat. עד שיפרוט לך הכתוב כדרך שפרט לך
בנזיר מחרצנים ועד זג. Ad sheyifrot lecha hakatuv kederach she-perat lecha be-Nazir
mechartzanim ve-ad zag. Okay. So that was a big re-quote of what
we just said. And now the גמרא Gemara says top of ל'
עמוד א': lamed amud alef: ולרבי אלעזר בן עזריה דקמוקים ליה למחרצנים
ועד זג לומר שאינו חייב עד שיאכל ב' חרצנים וזג. U-lerabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah dekamuqim leh lemechartzanim ve-ad zag lomar she-eino chayav ad sheyochal
bet chartzanim ve-zag. Okay, and now we're already partly up to an
answer about what we are about to say. This מחרצנים ועד זג
mechartzanim ve-ad zag if we were from the כלל ופרט klal u-ferat
camp... I need more colored markers up here. Anyway, if we were
from the כלל ופרט klal u-ferat camp... I know, I know, I'll
get them. If we were from the כלל ופרט klal u-ferat camp,
which what we're discussing right now, we're in the
כלל ופרט klal u-ferat camp, we need that, right exactly, say that
ten times fast.
כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-perat u-klal.
All right anyway, we need, we need, we need this as our
second פרט, perat, right? It's פרט כלל ופרט perat klal u-perat that
allows us to not say everything but to abstract כעין הפרט. ke-ein
ha-perat. But one minute, רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah
needed this to tell me that if I eat a כזית'ס kezayis's
worth of just skins or כזית'ס kezayis's worth of just pits I'm
not חייב. chayav. That this told me that I had to be
חייב chayav for the skins or the pits I need to have
at least two pits and one skin. Again that presumably is together
with needing a כזית. kezayis. So if I had just the flesh
I'd be חייב chayav in a כזית. kezayis. But if I had
just the... one wonders if I had just the flesh and some
skins to משלים. mashlim. But somehow anyway if I had just skins
itself I'm not חייב chayav until I have two pits and if
just pits I'm not חייב chayav until I have one skin. Okay,
so that's what, remember that's what he did with this in the
משנה. Mishnah. So he's using this for a very specific דרשה derasha
of the חיוב chiyuv by just skins or just pits. So how
can you use that for the final פרט? perat? This goes back
to the principle that if you're using it for one thing you
can't double-use a פסוק. pasuk. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says: ולרבי אלעזר בן עזריה דקמוקים ליה למחרצנים ועד זג לומר שאינו
חייב עד שיאכל ב' חרצנים וזג פרטא מנא ליה? U-lerabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah dekamuqim leh lemechartzanim ve-ad zag lomar she-eino chayav ad sheyochal bet
chartzanim ve-zag perata mena leh? Where does he get that final פרט
perat according to the פרט כלל ופרט perat klal u-perat approach? So
the גמרא'ס Gemara's first answer, and this answers the lingering question we
had: סבר לה כרבי אליעזר דדריש מיעוט וריבוי. Savar lah ke-Rabbi Eliezer
de-darish mi'ut ve-ribbuy. Oh now it's perfect! Because for רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, remember he ended here. Right? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer said מיעוט
וריבוי, mi'ut ve-ribbuy, that gave you your including everything except the stick,
except what is most dissimilar. And the whole point was he didn't
use the third thing because if you're from the ריבוי ומיעוט ribbuy
u-mi'ut camp you basically only need two terms, you don't need three
terms. So according to him, right, right the question was, was what
do you do with that third term? Oh it's perfect! רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer works together with רבי אלעזר בן עזריה. Rabbi Elazar ben
Azaryah. רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah uses this third
term to tell you something about two pits and a skin, so
he doesn't use it for a כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-perat u-klal.
So he therefore these two guys are working together. So you get
מיעוט וריבוי, mi'ut ve-ribbuy, you have everything except the stick and this
tells you a different הלכה halacha about skins and pits. Okay you
don't need three terms according to that camp. Okay that works very
good but then that forces the two of them to be working
together. Right nobody ever said that they agreed with one another in
נזיר, Nazir, but now we've sort of joined them. We've explained how
the מיעוט וריבוי mi'ut ve-ribbuy what he does with the third term
and what רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah does, what
does he do with the basic דרשה. derasha. Okay so they both
work together. This is a דרשה derasha that resides on two terms,
leaves the third term for this principle of two pits and a
skin.
Yeah and the other camp doesn't hold that principle.
And the other camp wouldn't hold that principle. So that would sort
of make the two debates dependent on one another which is possible
but we'd rather not say that. So the next answer is going
to pull back from that. At this stage we're saying they're interdependent
debates. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ואיבעית אימא, Ve-iba'it
eima, if you want you could say: כרבנן. Ke-rabbanan. No actually... No,
actually רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah would hold like
the רבנן, Rabbanan, and it would be פרט כלל ופרט, prat klal
u-prat, okay? דאי סלקא דעתך De-ee salka da'atcha כאמר k'ammar רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, because
and here's why it's possible for them to hold like one another.
Because the rabbis would say the following, meaning, let's say you're from
the camp and you darshen פרט כלל ופרט. prat klal u-prat. But
you're going to say, look, how do I know to say this
is a פרט? prat? Maybe the purpose of this, if I the
rabbis hold of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah, right?
We're now saying that even the פרט כלל ופרט prat klal u-prat
camp, the rabbis, can hold of רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah that darshens this פסוק. pasuk. But here's what they're going
to say. Yes, we do darshen this פסוק pasuk like רבי אלעזר
בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben Azaryah to tell you two pits and
a skin. But if that's all it was doing, if it wasn't
part of the פרט כלל ופרט, prat klal u-prat, if it's only
what it was doing was to tell you that דרשה, drasha, דאי
סלקא דעתך de-ee salka da'atcha as רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar
ben Azaryah said, לכתוב רחמנא להאי חרצנים וזג פרטי גבי פרטי. lichtov
Rachmana l'hai chartzanim v'zag pratei gabei pratei.
Then if all it was doing was to tell... yes, it is
telling you the הלכה halakha of two... of two pits and a
skin. That is what it's telling you. But it's also serving the
פרט כלל ופרט prat klal u-prat function. How? How can it do
two things? Because פרט כלל ופרט prat klal u-prat is about placement,
right? That's part of the whole דרשה drasha is based on placement.
So if all it was serving was this דרשה, drasha, write it
over here. Okay? Right? Why is it being placed after the כלל?
klal? So the words tell you the דרשה drasha of two pits
and a skin, the placement tells you the דרשה drasha of פרט
כלל ופרט. prat klal u-prat.
Syntax in other words, where the words are placed in the sentence?
Yes, exactly. Okay. So I forgot my high school grammar, I didn't
even remember that's what syntax meant. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. So it says, so, okay, למאי הלכתא כתביה בתר כללא?
l'mai hilchata katveih batar klala? Why is it written after the כלל?
klal? שמע מינה למידייניה בכלל ופרט. shma mina l'midaineih b'klal u-prat. Oh,
so yes, the דרשה drasha is like רבי אלעזר בן עזריה, Rabbi
Elazar ben Azaryah, two pits and a skin, but its placement tells
you that it's also a פרט כלל ופרט prat klal u-prat דרשה.
drasha. Okay. ואימא כולה להכי הוא דאתא? v'eima kullah l'hachi hu d'ata?
Alright, so how do you know to make רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Elazar
דרשה drasha at all? Maybe it's all just the פרט כלל ופרט
prat klal u-prat purposes? How do you know that there's something in
the... because it had to say חרצנים chartzanim if it had to
forbid the pits, and it had to say... I mean, it had
to say זג zag if it had to forbid the skin. So
if it had... if it's needed for its own purpose to forbid
the skins and the pits, and it's needed to be placed here
for the פרט כלל ופרט, prat klal u-prat, what's the basis? There's
nothing extra about it. What's the basis to make his דרשה? drasha?
So the answer is going to be pretty obvious, or it should
be based on what we said yesterday. ואימא כולה להכי הוא דאתא?
v'eima kullah l'hachi hu d'ata? Maybe it's all just coming for פרט
כלל ופרט prat klal u-prat and to tell you the basic הלכה
halakha that skins and pits is forbidden. No, אם כן לכתוב או
שני חרצנים או שני זגים. im ken lichtov o shnei chartzanim o
shnei zagim. Why didn't it say it... if the side had been...
או חרצנים וזגין o chartzanim v'zagin or שני זגים, shnei zagim, meaning
why does it say חרצנים ועד זג? chartzanim v'ad zag? It should
have said חרצנים ועד זגים chartzanim v'ad zagim or it should have
said חרצן וזג. chartzan v'zag. Right? Why is one in the plural
and one in the singular?
או שני זגים, o shnei zagim, או חרצן וזג. o chartzan v'zag.
למאי הלכתא כתב רחמנא חרצנים l'mai hilchata katav Rachmana chartzanim in the
plural ועד זג v'ad zag in the singular? שמע מינה למידרש ביה
כלל ופרט. shma mina l'midrash beih klal u-prat. So the placement of
this tells you the כלל ופרט klal u-prat principle, ואיכא נמי למידרש
ביה עד שיאכל שני חרצנים וזג. v'ika nami l'midrash beih ad sheyochal
shnei chartzanim v'zag. And the use of one in the plural and
one in the singular tells you two pits and a skin. Okay?
So it's very nice. You can do כלל ופרט וכלל. klal u-prat
u-klal. The placement here of a פרט prat tells you that we're
doing a... excuse me, פרט כלל ופרט. prat klal u-prat. And the
phraseology tells you two pits and a skin. Chavy, you look unhappy.
Why are you unhappy?
It's a little bit of violence done to the language there, that's
all.
What's violence done to the language? Why is pits in the plural
and and זג zag in the singular?
Look, because every grape
has seeds and then one...
because every grape has more than one seed and then the...
inside is seeds, right? That's always...
because every grape has plural... right, okay. I hear. Okay, I know.
I find it helpful to say that at some point there's a...
there's a tipping point. Like the חכמים Chachamim don't care about biblical
grammar and rhetoric.
They have their own hermeneutics.
So they're constantly dancing between the grammar and pushing the possibilities of
deconstruction in ways.
No, I
mean, I'm going to take it, I just don't like it.
Right.
Oh, shoot. So postmodern in some... if you like, retroject our terminology.
I'm
with you, man.
Alright. Alright.
Anyway, it is worth noting
by the way that if we're dealing with כלל ופרט וכלל, klal
u-prat u-klal, that's a...
that's a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael principle. And רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
is also דיברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam.
So whether we should be a little bit... anyway, you know, whether
it all works the same is a question.
Anyway, soon we will start the postmodern ישיבה yeshiva right after...
excellent.
Okay.
Moving on.
Now... intertextuality right now. What?
Now, thank you. Right. As Jenna points out. So for רבי... Rabbi...
so רבי אלעזר... Rabbi Elazar... For רב אליעזר Reb Eliezer we have
פרט וכלל. Prat u'Klal. We've got our abstraction. We've excluded the wood.
We don't know what we're doing with this term. Now רב אליעזר
Reb Eliezer could say, ah, I do hope like רב אלעזר בן
עזריה. Reb Elazar ben Azarya. I mean רב אלעזר בן עזריה Reb
Elazar ben Azarya doesn't hold like רב אליעזר, Reb Eliezer, but maybe
רב אלעזר Reb Elazar holds like רב אלעזר בן עזריה Reb Elazar
ben Azarya and he's going to say, yeah, this term I'm going
to use for something else. We don't know. Let's take a look
at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So,
okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this. ורבי אלעזר דדרש מיעוט וריבוי פרט כלל ופרט מנליה. V'Rabbi Elazar
de'darash Mi'et v'Ribah Prat Klal u'Prat minaley. Now here the גמרא Gemara
is sort of dropping Jenna's point. It's sort of assuming, I think
תוספות Tosfos says it explicitly, that רב אלעזר Reb Elazar might hold
like רב אלעזר בן עזריה. Reb Elazar ben Azarya. Like רב אלעזר
בן עזריה Reb Elazar ben Azarya could go either way as we've
just seen. But רב אלעזר, Reb Elazar, he's got this extra term
at the end, so we don't know what he's going to do
with it. He's going to do some other דרשה, drasha, okay, because
he doesn't really like need it for his פרט וכלל. Prat u'Klal.
His פרט וכלל Prat u'Klal ended here, so he'll use it for
some other דרשה, drasha, maybe רב אלעזר בן עזריה, Reb Elazar ben
Azarya, maybe some דרשה drasha we don't know about. But now what
the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, or it never really asks
and answers Jenna's question, תוספות Tosfos I think says, yeah, it could
very well be he holds like רב אלעזר בן עזריה, Reb Elazar
ben Azarya, who knows maybe he's doing something else with it. What's
that? What? Well, we don't we right, meaning before we said that
they were interdependent. Now we said רב אלעזר בן עזריה Reb Elazar
ben Azarya could go either way. רב אליעזר, Reb Eliezer, do we
have to limit him to רב אלעזר בן עזריה Reb Elazar ben
Azarya or not is not clear, but I think the גמרא Gemara
isn't exploring it because the fact that you've got something extra is
not doesn't sort of like weigh that heavily. Who knows what he
does with it? He does this דרשה, drasha, he'll do another דרשה,
drasha, right, he has his options open. But here the גמרא Gemara
is asking the following question, which is what does the מיעוט וריבוי
Mi'et v'Ribah camp do when it has three terms? Okay, meaning right,
here we're somehow assuming he's going to do something with the third
term, we don't know what. But would it ever do something with
three terms, what would it ever do when you actually had a
פרט כלל ופרט Prat Klal u'Prat scenario because in principle really you
only need like two terms, okay, and somehow for whatever reason, and
that's what some of these big תוספותים Tosfists are figuring out, is
that the גמרא Gemara assumes that they would like agree that when,
because here's the question, here's the way תוספות Tosfos frames the question.
Whenever there's a דרשה drasha in the גמרא Gemara of כלל פרט
וכלל, Klal Prat u'Klal, that's the more common one as opposed to
פרט כלל ופרט. Prat Klal u'Prat. But anyway, whenever there's one of
those דרשות drashas and those are very, very common in the גמרא,
Gemara, we don't see somebody come and say, wait, wait, wait, I
disagree with this whole thing. I דרשן darshen מיעוט וריבוי, Mi'et v'Ribui,
and I come up with a different conclusion and I've got an
extra third term floating around. Right, that's what we would be, right,
based on what we've seen here, you'd expect every time there's a
כלל פרט וכלל Klal Prat u'Klal or פרט כלל ופרט, Prat Klal
u'Prat, somebody would say, wait, wait, I basically have a different דרשה,
drasha, מיעוט וריבוי, Mi'et v'Ribah, I'm going to actually be broader and
more inclusive, I'll only exclude the most dissimilar, and I've got an
extra third term, right? But we don't find it. It's rare. All
of the very, very dominant voice is כלל פרט וכלל. Klal Prat
u'Klal. Okay, so basically what the גמרא Gemara is assuming here is
that even somebody from the ריבוי ומיעוט Ribah v'Mi'et camp would agree
that if you had three terms, and for whatever reason you could
not effectively do your ריבוי ומיעוט Ribah v'Mi'et דרשה drasha and then
do something with the third term, you would concede the point that
you can דרשן darshen it by a כלל ופרט. Klal u'Prat. Okay,
so that's what it's assuming. Because we just don't find as many
debates around this as we would expect. And therefore the גמרא Gemara
says, so where do you know that? Where do you find a
פסוק pasuk that teaches you that? Now, it's a funny question because
we're going to give פסוקים, psukim, but the פסוקים psukim don't prove
anything because the פסוקים psukim could be maybe I would have דרשן
darshened the פסוקים psukim ריבוי ומיעוט. Ribui u'Mi'et. We're just going to
show, oh look, here's a פסוק pasuk that's כלל פרט וכלל, Klal
Prat u'Klal, that's where this camp gets it from. The פסוק pasuk
doesn't prove you דרשן darshen כלל פרט וכלל. Klal Prat u'Klal. But
anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Where do
we get, because we find very often three terms and the מיעוט
וריבוי Mi'et v'Ribah does not speak up, and therefore we're going to
assume that that means the ריבוי ומיעוט Ribah v'Mi'et camp when it
can't, for whatever reason, if it's not doing its ריבוי ומיעוט Ribah
v'Mi'et דרשה drasha or for whatever technical reason maybe that doesn't work,
will concede the point of the כלל ופרט. Klal u'Prat.
Okay, so that's what it's assuming. Yes, Jenna. Meaning that a person
doesn't have to always be in one camp for the... Right, excellent.
So let me make a point about that which is there's an
excellent book which I have at home, which I was looking for
last night and couldn't find, I think it's one of those books
I lent out that nobody ever returned, so if anybody here or
anybody watching this or listening has my book, please get it back
to me. The name of this book is Y. J. Harris, it's
called How Do We Know This? And what he discusses with like
מנלן, Minalan, how do we know this? Or מנא הני מילי. Manei
hanei milei. Anyway, and what he discusses is right, the different hermeneutic
camps and how basically in the מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha and the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi they are very, I'm not going to say dogmatic, but
they're very like consistent. And they basically have this רב ישמעאל Reb
Yishmael camp of darshening and a רב עקיבא Reb Akiva camp of
darshening and if you're from one camp you only do one type
of דרשה, drasha, you never do the other type of דרשה drasha
and like there, exactly, you cannot switch over. And you know, and
the מדרשי הלכה Midreshei Halacha and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi are very consistent.
You get to the בבלי, Bavli, the בבלי Bavli just
randomly... applies different methodologies at different times, does not try to seek
for any type of consistency. I mean sometimes it drives תוספות Tosafot
crazy because תוספות Tosafot in one מסכת Masechet will say whoa whoa
whoa you just said רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer here is doing a
מיעוט וריבוי, Miut V'Ribbuy, but in this גמרא Gemara you said רבי
אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer is doing a כלל ופרט וכלל? Klal U'Prat U'Klal?
So how do you make sense of that? And he tries to
do somersaults or say things like, oh well when he can't do
a ריבוי ומיעוט Ribbuy U'Miut he does a כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal
Prat U'Klal, or whatever. The בבלי Bavli doesn't pay any attention to
any consistency, it just randomly sort of uses, you know, different types
of דרשות, drashos, you know, as is appropriate for the particular case.
Usually to fit an agenda right? Well, clearly, yeah. So right, it
does. So anyway, so I forget exactly the broader sort of points
he makes about that,
and he doesn't limit himself, by the way, to the תנאים Tannaim
and the גמרא, Gemara, like he even brings it up to modern
sort of scholarship and so on around these types of issues. So
it's very interesting about different types of hermeneutics and how consistent their
application is. But you are absolutely correct, this is classic בבלי Bavli
is like: oh, so how does מיעוט וריבוי Miut V'Ribbuy know to
use כלל ופרט וכלל? Klal Prat U'Klal? Like whoever said it does,
right? But תוספות Tosafot is saying, well, because we don't hear him
speaking up often enough, we're going to assume that he basically buys
in. We're not going to assume a rigid type of, you know,
membership in one opinion. Yes.
Let's clarify these תנאים, Tannaim, it's רבי אליעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Eliezer
ben Azariah and רבי אלעזר? Rabbi Elazar?
Yeah, thank you, right. It's רבי... Rabbi... I mean here it's spelled
אלעזר בן עזריה Elazar ben Azariah but yeah, it should be אליעזר.
Eliezer. Yeah, רבי אליעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi
Eliezer
ben Azariah and רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Yeah.
So I understand. So since it really is like a... looks like
a כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal Prat U'Klal, if you're going to really
be ממעט m'mait just the wood, then we're going to say that
חרצנים וזג chartzanim v'zag is coming for something else, like maybe to
teach you specifically to spit in a grape.
Exactly. Or something. Right. Okay, so let's go with... alright. Alright, let's
move on. Shhh! Everyone... what? רבי
אליעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Eliezer
ben Azariah and רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Which one holds which?
רבי אליעזר בן עזריה
Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah holds... רבי אלעזר בן עזריה Rabbi Elazar ben
Azariah holds two pits and a peel. Okay? So... and רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar is the one who's of the מיעוט וריבוי. Miut V'Ribbuy.
Let's go back. Alright, everybody שקט. sheket. Alright, let's go. Alright, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, והאי—where v'hai were we? רבי
אלעזר Rebbe Elazar דדריש didarish מיעוט וריבוי, Miut V'Ribbuy, פרט כלל ופרט
מנא ליה? prat klal u'prat minalei? How does he sometimes presumably—we're assuming
sometimes he holds a פרט כלל ופרט, prat klal u'prat, he doesn't
choose to דרשן darshan מיעוט וריבוי, Miut V'Ribbuy, where does he know
that that principle comes from? אמר רבי אבהו, Amar Rabbi Abahu, נפקא
ליה מהאי קרא, nafka lei mehai kra, from the following פסוק: pasuk:
וכי יתן איש אל רעהו חמור chamor, או שור או שה—פרט. Okay,
this isn't the obligation of שומרים, shomrim, of to be a, you
know, to watch items and your liability. So חמור, an ox or
a donkey or a sheep or
whatever—ox, donkey, or sheep, פרט, prat. that's specific. וכל בהמה, v'chol behemah,
any בהמה—כלל.
לשמור—חזר ופרט. Now where's לשמור חזר ופרט? lishmor chazar u'prat? Like where's
the לשמור פרט? lishmor prat? So תוספות Tosafot has a different גרסא.
girsa. תוספות Tosafot says
וכל—כלל, בהמה behemah לשמור—פרט. So anyway, it's already very forced. Okay, פרט
וכלל ופרט, prat u'klal u'prat, אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. ee
ata dan ela k'ein haprat. And therefore it's not limited to just
these types of things, it would be more broader, okay? It would
not just be limited to animals and so on. Okay, so somehow
from doing... now again, how do you know, even if we accept
that that's a פרט כלל ופרט, prat klal u'prat, how do you
know that that's the דרשה drasha he made? Maybe he made a
ריבוי ומיעוט Ribbuy U'Miut דרשה? drasha? Right? Just because you showed me
you can apply כלל ופרט וכלל Klal Prat U'Klal to a particular
פסוק pasuk doesn't show you that he learned it from there or
that's what he gets. So I really don't... I yeah, I really
don't understand it. רבא אמר, Rava amar, נפקא ליה מהאי קרא, nafka
lei mehai kra, from the following פסוק, pasuk, דבי קרבנות: d'bei korbanot:
ואם מן—פרט, if from—that's a פרט. prat, Now how from is a
פרט? prat. Because מן min somehow means not all, right? It's not
an entire set, it's some subset. Okay. הצאן, hatzon, אם מן הצאן
קרבנו, im min hatzon korbanvo, right? Is the פסוק. pasuk. Sheep—כלל, klal.
anything that's from the you know, from the צאן tzon category, from
the flock I should say. כשבים ועזים—חזר ופרט. Okay, and then specifically
lambs and goats, that's specific. פרט וכלל ופרט, prat u'klal u'prat, אי
אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. ee ata dan ela k'ein haprat. Now
besides that, that's like what? I don't get it. What can you
bring for a קרבן korban that's not a sheep or a goat?
And the other פסוק pasuk is about cows, right? It says ואם
מן הבקר קרבנו. v'im min habakar korbanvo. So what have you included
that wasn't explicit? So תוספות Tosafot says, well, I would have thought
that the word... what do you call it? כשבים ועזים kvasim v'izim
would have somehow been limited to one-year-old animals or something. So somehow
צאן tzon comes to include even two-year-old animals. So A, it's not
clear what exactly you're learning from the כלל ופרט וכלל, Klal Prat
U'Klal, it's not a good, nice, clear example of כלל ופרט Klal
Prat like this, where you clearly have specific, you clearly have right...
it's like cutting up a פסוק pasuk into tiny little divisions to
get a פרט וכלל ופרט. prat u'klal u'prat. And it's not clear
how this teaches a principle, it's just an assertion that he holds...
that this is what he does, this is what he does. In
this פסוק? pasuk? Yeah, I don't, so anyway, I really don't know
what to do with this גמרא. Gemara. Moving on, so אמר ליה
amar leh רב יהודה מדיסקרתא Rav Yehuda midiskarta לרבא le-Rava ולילף מהדין
קרא? ve-leilaf mi-ha-dain kra? Why did you jump to the פסוק pasuk
of sheep? Why didn't you start by the earlier פסוק pasuk by
the עולה, olah, by the cattle? מן Min פרט. prat, So מן
min again is from, not all. הבהמה Ha-behema כלל. klal, בקר וצאן
Bakar ve-tzon חזר פרט. hazar prat. פרט וכלל ופרט Prat u-klal u-prat
אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. i'ata dane ela k'ein ha-prat. Now
again, what are we including that wasn't already, you know, what's not
what's not בקר, bakar, right? What isn't that? So תוספות Tosafot says,
well maybe we're coming to include תוספות Tosafot says, I think he
says a שור הבר, shor habar, okay, which is some type of
a like of a wild ox, maybe it's a buffalo or something,
which is interesting, right, would that be included in בקר, bakar, would
buffalo could you bring a buffalo as a קרבן korban of the
ram to the מזבח, mizbeach, right, what? You wouldn't normally do that
anyway, I don't understand why why would you not normally do that?
Well oh, so there's a question is a
buffalo a חיה chaya or not.
There's a whole article about also American buffalo was
not known to the גמרא, Gemara, when the
ראשונים Rishonim talk about buffalo
they might be talking about a different species.
I can send you an interesting article about whether buffalo is a
חיה chaya or בהמה. behema. I'm sure you would be very interested.
What? The כוי? koy? Oh, I don't know, that was yesterday's discussion
why that was the כוי. koy. Anyway,
you got similar issue about wild sheep and wild goats. Right, right.
Anyway, okay, so why don't we do the דרשה זו. drasha zo.
אמר ליה, Amar leh, so now the question is why is בהמה
behema כלל? klal, Because according to this דרשה drasha the whole
point is that yes,
if we're talking about somehow to include a buffalo
or whatever
we're coming to include, it's something maybe
at the margins between חיה chaya and בהמה. behema. So בהמה behema
here is according to this דרשה drasha which is seen as a
כלל klal. is something that might have come to include even the
world of חיות chayas because that's the question. Does בהמה behema mean
like animal or does it specifically mean domesticated? Sometimes בהמה behema can
be include חיה, chaya, sometimes it's written exclude חיה. chaya. So from
this דרשה drasha that reads it as a כלל, klal? we're assuming
that it might have been even including חיה. chaya. So that's the
structure of the דרשה. drasha. So אמר ליה amar leh no, מהא
ליכא למשמע מינה. me-hai lekka le-mishma minah. You couldn't have learned it
out from that. דאי מהתם הוה אמינה הבהמה חיה בכלל בהמה. de-ee
me-hatam hava amina ha-behema chaya bi-khlal behema. So I would have said,
one minute, let me just wait, let me just remind myself, let
me check תוספות. Tosafot. Oh, the way he says it is that
since if בהמה behema would have been read as a כלל klal
to and therefore if it's going to be read as a כלל
klal, it would include חיה, chaya, then the words מן min would
not have had the effect of excluding them. If בהמה behema included
חיה, chaya, if that was explicitly like somehow included in the word
בהמה, behema, somehow the word מן min would not have been powerful
enough to exclude it. So let's see what the answer is. So
he says back, אמר ליה amar leh חיה בכלל בהמה? chaya bi-khlal
behema? How could I have thought that after you're done with the
פרטים pratim that חיה chaya means its most broadest sense? No, once
you look at the פרטים, pratim, it's clear that חיה chaya means
חיה. chaya. הכתיב בקר וצאן. Ha-ksiv bakar ve-tzon. No, בקר וצאן bakar
ve-tzon would have made it clear. That's exactly how the פרט כלל
ופרט prat klal u-prat would have functioned, that the פרטים pratim would
have made it clear that the word בהמה behema means only a
בהמה behema itself and
not חיה. chaya. הכתיב בקר וצאן, Ha-ksiv bakar ve-tzon, הוי ליה פרט
כלל ופרט אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט. havei lei prat klal
u-prat i'ata dane ela k'ein ha-prat. Fine, so one way or another
we're asserting that this camp of ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u-miut will hold
under some circumstances פרט כלל ופרט. prat klal u-prat. How we have
demonstrated it, we've used very weak פסוקים psukim for applying it, and
how that proves anything is unclear, but somehow this is a camp
that really holds of only two terms, and as תוספות Tosafot says,
we don't find this camp debating every time we say כלל פרט
וכלל, klal prat u-klal, so presumably there are times when there will
be three terms and for whatever reason they will actually at times
concede that you can use the other דרשה drasha as well. Okay,
and now the גמרא Gemara continues. ומנלן דהכי הוא? U-minalan de-hachi hu?
How do you know now the גמרא Gemara gets easier, okay, and
it sort of lays out actually I didn't even remember that this
פסוק pasuk which I used which is such a perfect פסוק pasuk
to demonstrate the כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal principle is the
פסוק pasuk the גמרא's Gemara now going to use. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara is going to say how we know the basic
idea of this hermeneutic of כלל פרט וכלל klal prat u-klal or
פרט כלל ופרט.
prat klal u-prat. What? That's the title of the book you just
mentioned, right?
How do we know this? Right,
exactly, exactly. Well, that's where he gets the phrase from. ומנלן דהכי
הוא? U-minalan de-hachi hu? And where do we know this is the
case? דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braisa: ונתת הכסף בכל
אשר
תאוה נפשך. Ve-nasata ha-kesef be-khol asher te-aveh nafshekha. You should give money
that for מעשר שני Maaser Sheni with everything your heart desires. כלל,
klal anything, that's a כלל. klal בבקר ובצאן וביין ובשכר Be-bakar u-ve-tzon
u-va-yayin u-va-shekhar פרט. prat.
So then it says specifically sheep and cattle and wine and mead.
ובכל אשר תשאלך נפשך, U-ve-khol asher tish'alekha nafshekha, whatever your heart wants.
כלל ופרט וכלל אי אתה דן אלא כעין הפרט.
klal u'prat
u'klal ee
ata dan ella k'ein haprat. מה הפרט מפורש, ma haprat meforash,
now how do we abstract this? פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע. pri mipri
vegidulei karka.
So פרי מפרי pri mipri means some type of an offspring of
an offspring, meaning that it's basically these are animals. So animals, you
know, sort of, you know, right, procreate, okay, and they're born from
one and from one another. So this would like exclude things that
are like, the Gemara says specifically to exclude things like salt or
what else does it also
or actually to like exclude like fish which like lay eggs, right,
but don't actually don't actually like procreate from one another, meaning yes,
you know, there's like they get the eggs get inseminated or whatever
but they don't actually are born, they're not given birth to from
one, you know,
live births, thank you. Although the funny thing is that we do
include birds. Yes.
So the funny thing why is the eggs, why is fish different?
Well, because it's meant to be probably also the second part of
גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, what? That they grow off of the land,
what?
I think some fish fertilize the eggs outside.
Oh, that's true, the eggs are fertilized outside where the birds are
fertilized in the animal and then they're laid. Right, no, no, I
think you're right. Okay. All right. So it
excludes and גידולי קרקע, gidulei karka, things that actually grow from the
ground, right, which is the second sort of category, ביין ובשכר, beyayin
uvesheichar, which excludes which excludes like water and salt, which are obviously
the most basic nutrients, but they don't grow, they're just taken from
the ground. Okay, so that's what's excluded is there has to be
some type of a birthed animal and
or growing from the ground. מה פרט מפורש, ma prat meforash, fruit
for instance.
Fruit, exactly. Fruit and birds and, you know, and all those types
of things. מה פרי מפורש פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע ma pri meforash
pri mipri vegidulei karka is also interesting that you could even use
fungi, sometimes fungi are excluded as גידולי קרקע gidulei karka because they
don't really, you
can use mushrooms?
You can use mushrooms, right. They don't really grow from the ground.
Anyway, okay, so that's what we exclude. מה פרט מפורש פרי מפרי
וגידולי קרקע אף כל פרי מפרי וגידולי קרקע. ma prat meforash pri
mipri vegidulei karka af kol pri mipri vegidulei karka. Okay, so that's
a nice perfect example of a כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'klal,
which it really almost like begs a hermeneutics, like אם מן הבקר
קרבנו בבקר זו im min habakar korbano babakar zo whatever, that like
there's nothing in that פסוק pasuk asks to be explained. But a
פסוק pasuk that has a big broad statement and then specific examples
and then a broad statement is like, okay, so what are the
rules? Like does it just this? Is it everything? Actually everything? So
that's where it sort of shows you that you need a hermeneutic.
Okay, and the פסוקים pesukim for השבת אבידה hashavat aveida also describe
it that way, right?
Right, exactly, exactly. מיתי. meiti. So now the Gemara says like this:
כלל ופרט וכלל כעין הפרט דנין. klal u'prat u'klal k'ein haprat danin.
So כלל ופרט וכלל klal u'prat u'klal we say it's like the
prat, okay. כלל דבתרא מאי אהני? klal de'basra mai ahani?
So right? So if you have כלל ופרט וכלל, klal u'prat u'klal,
it's like the prat. So what did the last כלל Klal, do?
Because otherwise you would have כלל ופרט klal u'prat and you would
have just had the prat, okay. This is just it's asking it
as a question, but it's really a way of explicating how what
are the different options are, right? כלל דבתרא מאי אהני אהני לאוסופי
כל דדמי ליה. klal de'basra mai ahani ahani le'osufei kol dedami leh.
That's coming to add everything similar to the prat. Because if you
had ended with כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, it would have just been
the prat, it would have just been the prat. The second כלל
klal. comes to say everything like the prat. וסו. vesu. Okay, that's
that. Now פרט וכלל ופרט כעין הפרט דנין. prat u'klal u'prat k'ein
haprat danin. So similar, פרט וכלל ופרט prat u'klal u'prat is like
the prat. So what would have been if you would have just
ended with פרט וכלל? prat u'klal? פרט דבתרא מאי אהני? prat de'basra
mai ahani?
What does the second פרט prat? do? If you had not had
the last one הוה אמינא נעשה כלל מוסיף על הפרט. hava amina
na'aseh klal mosif al haprat. So you would have had a פרט
prat. and a
כלל klal and it would have been everything. So the second פרט
prat. comes to pull you back. So in a כלל ופרט וכלל,
klal u'prat u'klal, the second כלל klal comes to broaden, and in
a פרט וכלל ופרט, prat u'klal u'prat, the second פרט prat comes
to pull back.
But they both wind up like the prat. So now the Gemara
is going to say is there any, well, is there any difference?
Exactly, exactly.
ומכדי. u'michdi. So let's take a look. תרי כללי ופרטי, trei klalei
u'prati, if you have two כללים klalim and a פרט, כלל ופרט
prat klal u'prat, וכלל, ותרי פרטי וכללי, ve'trei pratei u'klali, if you
have two פרטים pratim and a כלל, klal כעין הפרט דנין. k'ein
haprat danin. So three and four, they both of them we say
it's like the prat. מאי איכא ביני ביני? mai ika beini beini?
Is there any difference between the דרשה drasha of כלל ופרט וכלל
klal u'prat u'klal, and פרט וכלל ופרט? prat u'klal u'prat? Okay, if
you've ever had Michael, your question. איכא. ika. There is a difference.
כי הוה תרתין כללי ופרטי, ki hu tartein klalei u'prati, if you
have two כללים klalim and a פרט, prat so you have more
כללים, klalim, right? So it's broader. The majority is broad statements. אי
איכא פרטא דדמי ליה אפילו בחד צד מרבינן. ee ika prata dedami
leh afilu be'chad tzad marbinan.
So even if something is like the prat even in only one
characteristic, that's enough. It doesn't have to be super like the prat,
it's enough that it's somewhat like the prat, okay.
Sort of sounds like almost a מידת ריבוי, midat rivuy, it's close,
but close.
but it's excluding only what's most dissimilar. There you have to actually
point to some similarity, but it's enough to be similar in one
aspect. Okay. אפילו בחד צד מרבינן. Afilu bechad tzad marbinan. תרי פרטי
כלל, Trei pratei klal, if you have more פרטס, prats, if you
have פרט כלל ופרט, prat klal u'prat the limiting statements are the
more dominant ones. איכא פרטא דדמי משני צדדים, Ika prata dedami mishnei
tzadim, then מרבינן. marbinan. If
it has to be similar to the פרט prat in two characteristics.
בחד צד לא מרבינן,
Bechad
tzad
lo marbinan,
not, it's not enough to be similar in one character. Now תוספות
Tosafot goes back and tries to work it in with some of
the earlier things, because here we had פרט כלל ופרט prat klal
u'prat and it seemed like it was enough to be similar only
in one way and not in two ways, and you could worry
about that in תוספות. Tosafot. But at least what this גמרא Gemara
is saying is that these are pretty much the same but here
because there's more כללס, klals, it has to, it's somewhat broader. It
doesn't have to be as similar to the פרט prat as when
it's as when it's more פרט. prat, No, I don't want to
because the examples just confuse it all because it doesn't, this is
nice as a broad statement, but if you look at תוספות Tosafot
it doesn't really work. So anyway. What?
This and that. This and that.
It says it doesn't really work. What does the note say? Right,
I'm impressed that ארטסקרול ArtScroll actually says that it doesn't work.
It's supposed to explain, who, explain why in certain applications even the
פרט כלל פרט
prat klal
prat
sequence seems to require a dual similarity.
All right, there you go. וייטער. Weiter. All right, anyway, moving on.
Okay. But the גמרא Gemara is happy, so we're happy. Okay.
So one of the longest comments by שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz that I've ever
seen.
Really? ארטסקרול? ArtScroll?
It's about what you just said.
Okay fine. So איכא פרטא דדמי משני צדדים מרבינן בחד צד לא
מרבינן. Ika prata dedami mishnei tzadim marbinan bechad tzad lo marbinan. מכדי.
Michti. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
פרט וכלל נעשה כלל מוסיף על הפרט. Prat u'klal na'aseh klal mosif
al haprat. So you've got פרט וכלל, prat u'klal, so the כלל
klal it winds up all being collapsed into the כלל. klal, Okay.
ואיתרבי כל מילי, Ve'itravi kol milei, and everything is included. מיעוט וריבוי
נמי ריבוי הכל. Mi'at v'ribuy nami ribuy hakol. So מיעוט וריבוי mi'at
v'ribuy also winds up being a broad statement. So what's the difference?
This last sentence is what we had to know way at the
beginning. Okay. What's the difference between פרט וכלל prat u'klal which is
everything and מיעוט וריבוי, mi'at v'ribuy, isn't that everything? And the answer
is no, as we already know, מיעוט וריבוי mi'at v'ribuy doesn't ignore,
use both parts, so therefore it's not everything, it's everything except what's
most dissimilar, right? So that's going to be the difference. So the
גמרא Gemara says מיעוט וריבוי נמי ריבוי הכל ואיתרבי כל מילי מאי
איכא בין מיעוט וריבוי לפרט וכלל? Mi'at v'ribuy nami ribuy hakol ve'itravi
kol milei mai ika bein mi'at v'ribuy l'prat u'klal? What's the difference?
No, איכא, ika, there is a difference. דאילו פרט וכלל מרבינן אפילו
עלים ולולפים. De'ilu prat u'klal marbinan afilu alim v'lulafim.
פרט וכלל Prat u'klal we would include really everything, even the leaves
and the vines that go around the wood. ומיעוט וריבוי במיעוט וריבוי
U'mi'at v'ribuy be'mi'at v'ribuy we're going to exclude, we're going to exclude
something. We're not going to include everything and we're going to exclude
the thing that is most dissimilar. So what are we going to
exclude? So לולפים אין, lulafim in, yes we'll include the vine, but
עלים לא, alim lo, we will exclude the leaves, we are going
to exclude this principle here.
פרט וכלל Prat u'klal includes everything. So if you had just had
a פרט וכלל, prat u'klal, you would have included all parts of
the vine. If you didn't have a final פרט, prat, it would
have been completely inclusive. Including leaves. But מיעוט וריבוי mi'at v'ribuy ultimately
it excludes dissimilar things, so it excludes, it does exclude something and
it excludes the leaves. Now the problem is, as you might if
the folks that were paying attention, is that in the beginning of
the גמרא Gemara we said that the whole מיעוט וריבוי mi'at v'ribuy
basically excludes just the stick and it includes the leaves, right? Nobody
said the פרט וכלל. prat u'klal. פרט וכלל prat u'klal would have
included everything. But we did say the מיעוט וריבוי mi'at v'ribuy and
we said it includes the leaves and now we're saying it excludes
the leaves. So תוספות Tosafot tries to reconcile it by saying there
are edible leaves and inedible leaves. Okay. So what it's excluding is
the stick and the inedible leaves and it's including the vine and
the edible leaves. The problem is that the גמרא'ס Gemara's consistently only
talking about leaves and לולפים, lulafim, it's talking, it's using the same
term. Why yesterday did it mean edible leaves and today it means
inedible leaves? So I don't really know how to reconcile that, okay,
you know, but bottom line is that we do get the basic
parameters. The basic parameters is that פרט וכלל prat u'klal would have
included everything, so the גמרא Gemara is saying that nobody here דרשנס
darshens כלל ופרט פרט וכלל klal u'prat prat u'klal because it would
include everything. So basically either you're פרט prat כלל ופרט klal u'prat,
and then you are including only something similar to the פרט, prat
so they have to be basically types of grapes, could be spoiled,
could be unripe, types of grapes. Or you could be מיעוט וריבוי
mi'at v'ribuy and you'll be even more, and because you have only
two terms, you're much broader, okay, and you include everything, but
you include leaves and you include the vine but you are going
to exclude the wood. Okay, but there is a little contradiction in
terms of whether we're really excluding the leaves or not excluding the
leaves, but we will, we will leave that unresolved. Okay.
Why was that funny? Leaves. Oh, that was unintentional.
Understand, so if you have a כלל ופרט, klal u'prat, if you
just use a פרט, prat.
what's the point of the כלל?
klal So תוספות Tosafot says that asked before.
All right, so Michael says last point, Michael says if you have
a כלל ופרט, klal uprat. why did you need the כלל? klal.
So תוספות Tosafot says, yeah, like דיברה תורה. dibra Torah. דברה תורה
כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam.
Yeah, basically. Okay, which works not so bad because that is שיטת
רבי ישמעאל, shitas Rabbi Ishmael, which is דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם.
dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam. Okay.
So I have a more fundamental question.
Yes. Okay,
forget about the the whole thing. If the if the ברייתא braisa
said the rule is כלל ופרט אין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט, klal
uprat ein baklal ela mah shebaprat, okay, meaning whatever's in the פרט
prat, is in the כלל, klal? anything else is not, so why
why do we even have a כלל? klal? If we have a
if the Torah said why doesn't it just give the list of
the פרטים? pratim? Why give a כלל? klal, What's the point of
the כלל? klal? Right, that's what I asked you before. Oh, so
did you answer? I said that תוספות Tosafot says תוספות Tosafot says
it's basically דברה תורה כלשון בני אדם. dibra Torah k'lashon bnei adam.
Oh, okay, so it just doesn't doesn't it's just stylistic, it has
no actual application? It does have application! It teaches you that it's
a כלל klal? ופרט. If you didn't have the כלל, klal? it
would just be a list.